Okay, so in this section, we're going to
talk about two terms called Cost
Performance Index and Schedule Performance
Index.
All right, so let's talk about each of
these.
Now, both, cost performance index and
schedule performance index.
Both of these represent
the rate of performance,
but they'll look at them
in slightly different ways.
So cost performance index really is
looking at the rate of expenditure of your
funds, the rate of performance of your
money.
And basically what it's saying is,
for every dollar that I've spent,
how much dollars worth of work have I
actually done?
So for every dollar that
I've spent, how much
dollars worth of work
have I actually done?
So if I spend one dollar, do I do one
dollar's worth of work?
If that is a case, if I've
spent one dollar and I've
done one dollar's worth
of work, I'm right on budget.
That's where I'm expecting to be.
If, on the other hand, I spend $1 and I
have done a dollar and $10 worth of work,
that means I have done more work than what
I have paid for, therefore
I'm under budget.
If I spend $1 and I do
less than a dollar's worth
of work, let's say I do
$0.90 worth of work.
So for every dollar I spend, I've only
done $0.90 worth of work.
That means I'm more of a budget.
Now, the formula then for CPI,
right, for cost performance index,
is earned value over actual cost,
right?
Now, the formula is very similar to cost
variance.
Cost variance is earned value minus actual
cost.
In this case, we're just dividing them,
right?
That's your cost performance index.
So, in our example here, where we're doing
a 10-week project, and we're five weeks
into this 10-week
project, costing 100,000,
we're 40% complete, and we spent 60,000.
far.
So on previous videos then we had
calculated our own value to be 40,000,
actual cost to be 60,000.
So when you divide them, you get 0.67.
So we have a cost performance index of
0.67.
Is that good or bad?
That's really bad.
That's terrible.
I was basically saying
for every dollar that I
spend, my team only
does 67 cents worth of work.
My dollar is only working at a rate of 67
cents to the dollar.
My rate of expenditure or
funds, if you like, or my rate
of performance of my dollar
is 67%, which is not good.
So it basically tells me that I am over
budget.
I'm a cost performance index.
If it's less than one, it means that I'm
over budget.
So this case, less than one in bad is bad,
greater than one is good, right?
If I'm working at a rate greater than
100%, then that's good.
Now, same with Schedule Performance Index,
SPI.
Schedule Performance Index is looking at
your rate performance of the actual work.
Have we worked at 100% rate so far?
So if we've been building this road, we
should have built five
sections of the road.
If we had built five sections of the road,
we worked at 100% rate.
That means our SPI will be one.
If our SPI is greater than one,
right?
Basically, if we've worked at a 120% rate,
then we're ahead of schedule.
If we've worked out a 90% rate,
then we're behind schedule.
So the formula for SPI then is earned
value over planned value.
Again, very similar to schedule variance.
Schedule variance is earned value minus
planned value.
In this case, you're dividing them.
So basically it's saying the rate
performance of the work achieved so far,
in this case then, our earned value is
40,000, planned value was 50,000,
that we calculated in a previous video.
And so SPI then is 0.8.
Our rate of performance of the work that
we've achieved so far is basically 80%.
Is that good or bad?
Again, that's really bad.
We've only worked at a rate of 80%.
That's not good.
So with either of these,
the cost performance
index, our schedule performance index.
Any number that's less than one is not
good.
Greater than one is good.
So in this case then, we've only worked at
an 80% rate, which makes sense because
remember what the scenario is,
right?
We should have built five sections of the
road so far.
We've only built four sections of the
road.
Four sections is 80% of five sections.
That's basically what we've calculated.
Five sections of the road is worth
$50,000.
Four sections of the road is worth
$40,000.
$40,000 is 80% of $50,000.
That is basically what we've calculated
here.
Alright, so these are
two of the indices, then,
two of the three indexes that I mentioned.
So these are then in terms of a 1,
right, when you multiply by 100,
then you get a percentage.
And these are showing the actual rate of
performance then, the rate of performance
of your dollar and the rate of performance
of the actual work.